בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is פ"ג Peh gimmel and
everybody needs to get out if not their thinking caps, their calculators
for today's דף. daf. There's a lot of computation.
So we pick up six lines from the bottom on פ"ב עמוד
ב' Peh bet amud bet and we're going to be figuring out
the exact amount that is in the מזון שתי סעודות, mazon shtei
seudot, the two meals worth. And this becomes important not just for
the size of the bread for the עירוב eruv or for the
עירובי תחומין, eruvei t'chumim, which can be of not only of bread,
but also for the whole idea of the פרס, pras, the half
loaf and the size of one סעודה, seuda, which is so relevant
for other areas of הלכה. halacha. So we pick up now with
six lines from the bottom. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר. Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka omer. If you'll remember רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka said it is the type of bread that can be
bought for a כיכר kikar for a פונדיון pundion when four סאים
se'im of flour presumably go for a סלע. sela. So to remind
you this fourth quadrant of the board,
four
סאה, se'ah, one סאה se'ah equals six קב. kav. Actually I have
all these charts downstairs. Four סאה se'ah is 24 קב. kav. Okay
and there are 48 פונדיון pundion for סלע. sela. This is a
coin. This is a coin and this is a volume of measurement.
So that means if it's cost one פונדיון pundion for a loaf
of bread and this is the rate that flour is going for,
so then basically a loaf is a half a קב. kav. You
see that? If for every two פונדיון pundion you buy one קב,
kav, so for one פונדיון pundion you get a half a קב.
kav. Okay so that's what he said.
And the other opinion said, we might as well repeat it, שתי
ידות לכיכר משלוש לקב. Shtei yodot l'kikar mi-shalosh l'kav. So the position
of רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, okay so this is רבי יוחנן
בן
ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said you
have three loaves
equals
a קב. kav. So one loaf equals a third of a קב.
kav. Okay but one loaf equals a third of a קב, kav,
but he said, or at least he's dealing with loaves that are
a third of a קב, kav, there's no objective reality how big
a loaf of bread is. But what he added to was he
said two thirds, שתי ידות, shtei yodot, two thirds of that. So
for him this is a סעודה seuda is times two thirds is
two ninths of a קב kav is a סעודה. seuda. Okay and
for רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka a סעודה seuda
is a half of a קב. kav. Okay so that is their
debate. Alright so let's see where that goes. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this. רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר. Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka
omer. תנא, Tanna, we taught in the ברייתא, Braita, וקרובין דבריהם להיות
שוין. Ukrovin divreihem l'hiyot shavin. They're pretty much the same thing. They're
very close. So now that's not at all close, right? You'd have
to be a master of math to see that a half and
two ninths have quite a difference from one another. So the גמרא
Gemara says מי דמי? Mi dami? What do you mean? How can
you compare them? לרבי יוחנן ארבע סעודות לקב. L'Rabbi Yochanan arba seudot
l'kava. For רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan right if there is oh I'm
this is two סעודות seudot worth. I might have said it wrong,
right? Because we're here defining the loaf of bread that's worth two
סעודות. seudot. Okay so that's two סעודות. seudot. Okay according to these
these are two opinions about what is two סעודות. seudot. So for
him a half of a קב kav is two סעודות. seudot. Okay
so then what does that mean? That means so לרבי יוחנן l'Rabbi
Yochanan where are
we? מי דמי? Mi dami? לרבי יוחנן ארבע סעודות לקב. L'Rabbi Yochanan
arba seudot l'kava. There are four סעודות seudot for every קב. kav.
Right? If a half of a קב kav is two סעודות, seudot,
then a quarter of a קב kav is one סעודה, seuda, right?
Is one meal's worth. So that means that there are four meals
per קב. kav. Okay so
that's לרבי שמעון תשע סעודות לקב. l'Rabbi Shimon tisha seudot l'kava. According
to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon if two ninths of a קב kav
is two סעודות, seudot, then how much is one סעודה? seuda? One
ninth. So how many סעודות seudot do you get out of a
קב? kav? Nine. Okay? You don't get it?
It's just a distance difference between four and nine.
It's a big difference. That's what the גמרא Gemara is saying. So
they're not close to being the same. Okay so אמר רב חסדא,
Amar Rav Chisda, צא מהם שליש לחנווני. Tze mehem shelish l'chanvani. רב
חסדא Rav Chisda says no no no here's the problem. We were
talking about the price of the wheat or the price of whatever,
that was the wholesale price. Okay we're talking now about how much
the storekeeper, the retailer charges. So he says the retailer okay basically
ups the price. So if he's charging a פונדיון pundion he's not
going to charge a פונדיון pundion for a half of a
קב. kav. He's going to sort of raise the price by a
third. So he's charging a פונדיון pundion not for a half, but
for two thirds of this amount. So it's times two thirds right?
So he's actually charging...
that's just what the גמרא Gemara said. That's just profit margin. Actually
the wholesale cost is one פונדיון pundion for a half קב. kav.
But he's only going to sell two-thirds of that for the one
פונדיון pundion because that's his profit margin. So he's only selling, he's
only selling two-thirds times one-half is one-third. Okay, so wait, you're allowed
to take that much profit margin?
Yeah, the
הלכה halakha about overcharging is not a degree of the profit margin.
The הלכה halakha of overcharging is about comparable to the going rate.
Okay, so anyway, so for him it's one-third, it's he's really selling
one-third of a קב, kav, and that's what is for two סעודות.
se'udot. Okay, but the problem is one-third of a קב kav for
two סעודות se'udot still means one סעודה se'uda is a sixth, right?
So you still have a difference between a sixth and a
ninth. Wait, wait, is he talking wholesale or retail? Yeah, he's talking
retail. So the גמרא Gemara says, וכתי למר תשעה ולמר ששה. vakati
lemar tisha ulemar shish. So for him, right again, two-ninths for two
סעודות se'udot become one-ninth for one סעודה, se'uda, and therefore it's nine,
nine סעודות se'udot per קב. kav. For him, one-third for two סעודות
se'udot becomes one-sixth for a סעודה. se'uda. So it's still a difference
of six to nine. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says they're still
not close. וכתי למר תשעה ולמר ששה. vakati lemar tisha ulemar shish.
אלא כי אידך דרב חסדא. Ela ki idach deRav Chisda. Okay, like
another teaching of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. דאמר de'amar who says, טפי
מהן פלגא לחנוני. tfei mehen palga lechanvani. The חנוני chanvani actually gets
a fifty percent, he charges a fifty percent uptick in the price,
that's his profit margin. Okay, so means what? Go back to here.
He wholesaled it, he got a half of a קב kav for
a פונדיון. pundion. But he's going to get a fifty percent margin,
so he's only going to sell a quarter of a קב kav
for a פונדיון. pundion. Okay, you get it? So he's basically doubling
or whatever. So he's selling a quarter of a קב kav for
a פונדיון. pundion. So if a quarter of a קב kav is
two meals, right? So then an eighth of a קב kav is
one meal. So and he says a ninth of a קב kav
is one meal. So a ninth and an eighth now we're talking
pretty close. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says וכתי יפצו ביניהון
וכתי למר תשעה ולמר תמני. vakati yaftzu beineihon vakati lemar tisha ulemar
tmanei. One is eighth of a קב, kav, one is nine meals
and one is eight meals. היינו דאמרי בקרובין דבריהם להיות שוין, Hainu
de'amri bikrovin divreihem lihyot shavin, that they're pretty close to the same
position. Okay, now, קשיא דרב חסדא אדרב חסדא. kashya deRav Chisda a-deRav
Chisda. Now we have a contradiction of רב חסדא. Rav Chisda. In
one place he said the חנוני chanvani does a you know a
one-third profit margin, in another place he says a half, a fifty
percent profit margin. So the גמרא Gemara says לא קשיא, lo kashya,
it's not difficult. הא דקיהב בעל הבית ציבי הא דלא קיהב בעל
הבית ציבי. Ha deka'yah ba'al habayit tzivei, ha deloka'yah ba'al habayit tzivei.
The question is, I might have said it wrong, because I said,
I was treating the חנוני chanvani as the retailer, but actually the
חנוני chanvani here is the guy who's baking the bread. So what
he was doing is he was charging the prices were for the
flour and his profit margin, now it makes also more sense, he's
not just getting the profit
for being the retailer, he's getting the profit actually for being the
producer of the bread, right? For the effort of baking the bread.
So it says the original price was for the flour, then he
got a profit margin of a third or fifty percent or whatever
it is because he actually baked the bread. So what determines whether
it's a third or whether it's a half? So the גמרא Gemara
says, is the בעל הבית ba'al habayit providing the wood? Okay, so
if you provide the wood, he'll only charge you for his effort
and whatever, he'll only get a third of a profit margin. If
you don't provide the wood, he's going to charge a half of
a profit margin. Okay, so that is anyway
two ways of understanding that the משנה mishna gave the amount of
flour, but you have to also incorporate the profit margin so you
can figure out the amount of bread that we're actually talking about.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, חצי לבית המנוגע
וחצי חציה לפסול את הגויה. chetzi lebayit hamenuga vechetzi chetziyah lifsol et
hageviyah. So you have this loaf of bread, which is half of
it. Now, how big is this loaf of bread? So one thing
you've got to know, so let's get back to what we said.
So for
רבי יוחנן בן ברוקה, Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, we have now said
that the loaf of bread is a quarter of a קב. kav.
Okay, and for רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, we said that the loaf
of bread is two-ninths of a קב. kav. So half of that
is, which is one סעודה, se'uda,
is an eighth of a קב kav and or here one-ninth of
a קב. kav. That's one סעודה's se'uda worth. Okay, now how big
is a קב? kav? Okay, how many ביצים beitzim is a קב?
kav? So a קב kav is twenty-four ביצים, beitzim, I believe I'm
right. Yes, a קב kav is twenty-four ביצים. beitzim. So an eighth
of a קב kav for him becomes three ביצים. beitzim. And a
ninth of a קב kav for him becomes, wait, did I do
that right?
A ninth of a קב... kav...
so yeah, they're not going to be... twenty-four...
ninth of a קב... kav...
hold on I'm doing something, am I doing something wrong? One minute.
Two-thirds.
No, no, no.
Here's what I'm doing wrong. One minute. Two-ninths was when he... When
he did two-thirds of the loaf. Remember, he says that the loaf
was, he says that the loaf was a third. But then he
said for the issue of עירוב eruv he used two-thirds of a
loaf. Remember that? He said two-thirds of the loaf. But the loaf
was a third of a קב. kav. So actually now when we're
talking about, when talking about עירוב eruv it was one-eighth versus two-ninths.
But when we're talking about the actual size of the loaf, it's
actually one-third versus one-quarter. And for everything else, even for רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon we use the size of the loaf. The two-third loaf
was just for, the two-thirds for him, that was just for the
עירוב. eruv. But everything else is going to be based on the
loaf size. So one-third of a קב, kav, so if you do
half of that for the one סעודה seuda measure, it's a sixth.
And a sixth of a קב kav if you have twenty-four ביצים
beitzin is four ביצים. beitzin. So right now the argument is, is
the size of one סעודה, seuda, the half loaf, which is basically
the פרס, pras, כדי אכילת פרס, kedai achilat pras, which is that
critical measurement in all those areas of הלכה, halacha, is that three
ביצים beitzin or four ביצים? beitzin? That is the debate.
Neither of which is that large.
What? Neither of which is that large.
Right. And so his loaf of bread is a quarter of a
קב, kav, his loaf of bread is a third. He doesn't even
use the full loaf for the עירוב, eruv, but this is the
size of two meals, and then half of it, the פרס, pras,
is this debate and it's between
three ביצים beitzin and four ביצים. beitzin. You have to eat like
a כזית kezayit on פסח Pesach and you say a כביצה kebeitza
is bigger than it gets to be huge. Right.
So, so we'll talk about how this all works. So חציה לבית
המנוגע, chetzyah l'veit hamenuga, so the size of one meal for the
צרעת tzaraat house, the חצי חציה לפסול את הגוויה. chatzi chetzyah lifsol
et hageviyah. Oh, I think I, I think I jumped ahead again.
This is one סעודה seuda not a פרס, pras, excuse me. This
is one סעודה's seuda worth, but half, no, one minute. What did
I do wrong?
חציה, chetzyah, no, that's right. Hold on.
Right. No, I did it right. I did it right. No matter
what they say. Last time I thought I was, I was wrong,
I was mistaken. Okay, so, so this is, so what did I
write here? Anyway, this is one סעודה seuda which is a פרס.
pras. I was right. Okay, fine. That's, that's your פרס. pras. So
that is a פרס pras and that's between three or four ביצים.
beitzin. Okay, now half of that, that's also the amount of size
that the בית המנוגע beit hamenuga going into a house of leprosy
because it's the time it takes to eat one meal. So this
is the one meal, this is the כדי אכילת פרס. kedai achilat
pras. Half of that, which is one and a half ביצים beitzin
or two ביצים, beitzin, is if you eat טמא tamei food you
become טמא. tamei. We're not going to, we're not going to like
spend too much time on that. But now תנא, Tanna, top of
פג עמוד א, pei gimmel amud aleph, we're going to focus on
the next point. וחצי חצי חציה, v'chatzi chatzi chetzyah, a half of
the half of the half, okay, so a half of this last
amount, is לטמא טומאת אוכלין. l'tamei tumat ochlin. So this amount is
one meal, this is a half a meal, okay, and then, and
this is for פסול גוויה. pissul geviyah. But now what we're looking
at is טומאת אוכלין, tumat ochlin, because the importance about this is,
we know the size of טומאת אוכלין. tumat ochlin. How much food,
what is the size of a piece of food that it can
become טמא tamei or transfer the טומאה? tumah? There's different issues about
that, but the minimum size of a food in the area of
becoming, of טומאה, tumah, so it's a half of a half. So
it would be either three-quarters or one ביצה. beitza. Now, for those
who remember whenever טומאת אוכלין tumat ochlin has come up in the
past in the גמרא, Gemara, the size we always went by was
one ביצה. beitza. Okay, that's the standard size of טומאת אוכלין, tumat
ochlin, which seems, if you go all the way back, to be
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon position. Okay. So again, the debate is a
loaf, a half a קב kav or a third of a קב,
kav, which is basically the big issue then is the
פרס, pras, one סעודה seuda worth, three ביצים beitzin or four ביצים.
beitzin. And a quarter of that, we'll just ignore the middle case,
a quarter of that is the size of טומאת אוכלין. tumat ochlin.
Now I should say something about the הלכה. halacha. Since we tend
to פסקן pasken one ביצה beitza is טומאת אוכלין, tumat ochlin, which
פסקן, pasken, which is רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, right, it's four divided
by a quarter, that would mean we would say כדי אכילת פרס
kedai achilat pras is four ביצים, beitzin, right? And that now, then
the question becomes, how many כזיתים kezayitim in a ביצה? beitza? That's
one way of doing it. Okay, so רש"י Rashi says, so if
we פסקן pasken this, רש"י Rashi says two זיתים zeitim in a
ביצה beitza and כדי אכילת פרס kedai achilat pras equals eight כזיתים.
kezayitim.
רמב"ם, Rambam, however, פסקן, paskens, or actually I think he has different
פסקין psakin in different places, but there's the other פסק psak that
you take three ביצים, beitzin, you פסקן pasken רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא,
Rabbi Yochanan ben Beroka, but interestingly, פסקן paskens that three כזיתים kezayitim
in a ביצה. beitza. So that then leads to times three to
nine כזיתים. kezayitim. So if you want to actually know what is
the size of כדי אכילת פרס kedai achilat pras להלכה, l'halacha, okay,
obviously it all then hinges on what is the size of a
כזית, kezayit, but this debate of three versus four also depends on
the debate of what is the size of a כזית kezayit and
becomes this debate of eight כזיתים kezayitim versus nine כזיתים. kezayitim. That's
the הלכה. halacha. That is the practical different opinions. About the size
of כדי אכילת פרס K'dei Achilas Pras so when you're trying to
figure out like how quickly do I have to eat the מצה
matzah on פסח Pesach or whatever I mean anyway just eat it
at a normal pace and you're fine. But anyway there are this
debate of three ביצים beitzim or four ביצים beitzim which translates into
eight versus nine כזיתים kezeisim which is not reconciled are different positions
out there. But the way it translates into טומאת אוכלים tumas ochlim
is three quarters of a ביצה beitzah or one ביצה. beitzah. So
let's take a look now at what the גמרא Gemara says. Yes.
Eggs come in
different...
yeah. In a... when you bake it's...
right there's large and extra large and jumbo right I know I
know
and they've gotten bigger over time.
Right so there's you know there's all these questions about being
so precise. Well they say a standard size but what is a
standard size? You know olives are probably more standard sizes than eggs
which is why it's helpful to translate that into olives but then
there's that debate.
And olives actually haven't gotten bigger.
Right probably there's that debate whether three or two olives to an
egg probably based on this issue. If you actually think about it
three olives to an egg you're still talking you're talking about a
pretty darn small egg even three olives let alone two olives. So
yeah you're right.
They are talking about volume. Okay all right well we're going to
talk about that. So let's now see. Okay so the גמרא Gemara
says ותנא דידן מאי טעמא לא תנא טומאת אוכלים u'tana didan mai
taama lo tana tumas ochlim why didn't our תנא tana you know
go to the next stage and get
to a quarter an eighth of the original number and get to
this issue about the טומאה tuma of foods? משום דלא שוו שיעורייהו
להדדי shum d'lo shavu shiuraya l'hadadi
because it's not exactly precise it's not exactly a half of the
previous amount. Why not? I mean on the board it's exactly a
half but now the גמרא Gemara is going to say actually our
numbers until now were not totally precise and this is going to
be interesting. דתניא d'tanya we taught in a ברייתא braisa כמה שיעור
חצי פרס kama shiur chatzi pras how much is a half a
פרס? pras? בי ביצים חסר קימעא דברי רבי יהודה. bei beitzim chasar
kima divrei rabbi yehuda. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says two ביצים beitzim
right following the ריקמן Rikman position two ביצים beitzim but not exactly.
Two ביצים beitzim minus a little bit okay which basically means remember
our starting point was the size of a loaf. Since when is
the size of a loaf exactly precise in terms of how much
flour you use or what its volume is? So he actually says
you know these numbers until now were not 100% precise and actually
the two ביצים beitzim is not two ביצים beitzim it's 1.98 or
whatever it is two minus a little bit. Whereas טומאת אוכלים tumas
ochlim this size of טומאת אוכלים tumas ochlim is actually precise either
one or three quarters. So what it's saying is the reason our
תנא tana did not give the טומאת אוכלים tumas ochlim is these
numbers are precise whereas all of these numbers because this was a
number חז"ל Chazal just defined. A ביצה beitzah or normally we go
by a ביצה beitzah whereas all of these were based on the
amount of food that you eat and you know it wasn't given
like a and therefore it was a function of that and it
therefore was a little bit imprecise. That's the best I can say
okay because fundamentally this is about how much food do people eat
so that's not as precise as defining כזית kezayis or כביצה kebeitzah
and so on. So that's why we didn't give this because this
is precise and this is imprecise. How imprecise is this? Two ביצים
beitzim don't mean two ביצים beitzim it means minus a little bit.
Okay בי ביצים חסר קימעא דברי רבי יהודה. bei beitzim chasar kima
divrei rabbi yehuda. רבי יוסי אומר Rabbi Yossi omer the opposite.
בי ביצים שוחקות bei beitzim sochakos two ביצים beitzim שוחקות sochakos like
you know normally we use שוחקות sochakos when you're talking about a
טפח tefach because when you laugh your hand shakes a little bit
and therefore it's not like a tightly measured it's a loose measure.
So two ביצים beitzim a loose measure of two ביצים beitzim which
means 2.1 okay. So one says it's 1.9 and the other says
it's 2.1. Now שיער רבי shier rabbi now רבי Rabbi basically estimated.
רש"י Rashi says that רבי Rabbi took a like סאה seah and
he then tried to break it down into how many eggs we
were talking about and he estimated that it was בי ביצים ועוד
bei beitzim ve-od two ביצים beitzim plus a little bit. So the
way רש"י Rashi says it not the way I said before that
it was a question about how much bread to you know that
it's imprecise because how much bread people eat but the measure of
the number of ביצים beitzim to a קב kav is not an
exact number. We were assuming right we were assuming 24 ביצים beitzim
to a
קב kav right and רש"י Rashi says that רבי Rabbi had a
סאה seah which is even bigger which is six קב kav and
he tried to measure it in terms of ביצה beitzah and it
wasn't exactly precise. So what number did he come up with? He
came up with if you did all the divisions you would not
be left with two but you'd be left with בי ביצים ועוד
bei beitzim ve-od two plus a little bit. Okay so כמה ועוד
kama ve-od how much is that little bit extra which funny you
didn't ask it before but it's asking it here according to
רבי. Rabbi. So it said אחד מעשרים דביצה echad mi-esrim d'beitzah so
1/20th. Somehow there was a tradition that 1/20th was the you know
is how is what is was the amount that it was off.
So according to רבי Rabbi it's 2 and 1/20th right 2 and
1/20th ביצים beitzim you know and you add all you multiply. all
that together and you get the size of a סאה. Seah. So
a סאה, Seah, which is the big size that we've kept on
subdividing, according to him is not a precise number of ביצים, Beitzim,
it's actually subdivides into when you get to this smaller amount two
and one twentieth. All right, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. דאילו, De'ilu, so the גמרא Gemara says וקא מברייא. veka mavraya.
דאילו גבי טומאת אוכלים, De'ilu gabei tumat ochlim, so there you see
that when it comes to all of these measurements based on a
סאה, Seah, it's not precise in terms of number of eggs. But
by טומאת אוכלים, Tumat ochlim, that is a precise number. תני תנא
בברייתא, Tani tana bivraita, רבי נתן רב דוסא אומר Rabbi Natan, Rabbi
Dosa omer כביצה Kebeitzah שאמרו she'amru כמוה כקליפתה. kamocha kekliptah. When they
said an egg, it was exactly one egg and one egg including
the shell. וחכמים אומרים Vachachamim omrim כמוה בלא קליפתה, kamocha belo kliptah,
one egg minus the shell. Okay, but whatever it is, there it
was they're talking about precise, although there is a debate exactly which
type of egg we're talking about, but the reason the גמרא Gemara
says we didn't mention טומאת אוכלים Tumat ochlim in our משנה Mishnah
is this is given in a precise amount based on eggs. This
is an exact number one egg or one egg following רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. All of this were divisions of a קב. Kav. And
a קב Kav is not exactly precise in the number of eggs.
Like saying how many centimeters to an inch? Roughly 2.5, but it's
not exactly, right?
It's actually exactly 2.54.
Right. So a קב Kav is not exact in the number of
eggs, so all of these numbers which are based on a קב
Kav are a little bit off. And this number is precise. Okay.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבא בר פפא
אמר רב חסדא. Amar Rabbah bar Papa, amar Rav Chisda. זו דברי
רבי יהודה ורבי יוסי. Zu divrei Rabbi Yehuda v'Rabbi Yosi. This issue
about the one egg size is whether it's with the shell or
without the shell is the position of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and
רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yosi. אבל חכמים אומרים, Aval chachamim omrim, there's another
position out there which is כביצה ומחצה kebeitzah umechtza שוחקות. sochakos. That
actually, I'm sorry, that's the difference of, I'm sorry, not the one
egg, but the question about two eggs minus a little or two
eggs plus a little is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi and רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. But the חכמים Chachamim say it's one and a half
eggs plus a little. Okay, one and a half eggs measured loosely.
So obviously, meaning until now we've been talking about this number and
the two plus a little, two minus a little, and he says
wait a minute, there's another opinion out there that's one and a
half, not two. The position of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא. Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka. So he's just reminding us don't just focus on the
two becoming one, there's also another position out there of the one
and a half. So the גמרא Gemara says ומאן חכמים, Uman chachamim,
who is this חכמים? Chachamim? רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא. Rabbi Yochanan ben
Broka. פשיטא, Pshita, of course, we can do the math too. We
were talking about the position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and talking
about two eggs. But according to רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan
ben Broka it'd be one and a half שוחקות sochakos אתא לאשמועינן.
ata l'ashmieinan.
No, that's true, what he's coming to tell me is is that
within רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's one and a half, it's one and
a half plus a little. Okay, it's not one and a half
minus a little, it's not one and a half exactly, it's one
and a half plus a little. So what do we have? All
of these positions are subdivisions of a סאה. Seah. And we have
said that a סאה Seah is not exactly measured in eggs. So
when you get down to here, which is a bit, you know,
after you've divided it, you know, ten times or however many times,
you have the position of either two and two is either plus
or minus a little bit, or one and a half which is
plus a little bit. Those are the different positions and determined about
how exactly big a סאה Seah is and or how exactly big
you know a loaf of bread is. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says like this. כי אתא
רב דימי, Ki ata Rav Dimi, when רב דימי Rav Dimi came
from ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, אמר, amar, he said שיגר בוניס, shigar
Bunis, so this person by the name of בוניוס Bunios sent
לרבי leRabbi מודייא דקונדיס modaya deKundis from קונדיס, Kundis, very interesting names.
I'm sorry, no, in רש"י Rashi we read it different. I'm sorry,
שיגר, shigar, I read it wrong. שיגר בוניס לרבי, shigar Bunis leRabbi,
בוניס Bunis sent to רבי Rabbi מודייא דקונדיס. modaya deKundis. This is
some type of a word meaning a סאה Seah measure, I don't
know how that exactly translates.
Okay דניאוסא deNi'usa from this place of ניאוסא. Ni'usa. He sent him
a סאה Seah measurement from there. ושיער רבי Veshi'er Rabbi and רבי
Rabbi estimated מאתן ושבע עשרה ביעי ma'atan v'shiva asrei bei'ei 217 eggs
to a סאה. Seah. Now let's figure out how many eggs there
are in a סאה. Seah. Okay because this is not as hard
as you think it's going to be. Okay, one סאה, Seah, one
סאה Seah equals six קב, kav, okay. Each קב kav is 24
eggs. So what's 6 times 24?
144. 144 eggs. Okay, now רבי Rabbi came up with 217. So
we're going to have to figure out how 144 became 217.
So you figure two and a little bit and you multiply that
all,
yeah it won't get that much. The גמרא Gemara knows that, but
it's not going to get that high. So the גמרא Gemara says
like this. גמרא Gemara says הא סאה דהיכא, ha se'ah deheicha,
which type of סאה Seah it is? Because we're going to find
out that there were you know I think you have this like
you have two types of tons, like an English ton and another,
you have sometimes the same name of a measurement that means different
things in different contexts. So the גמרא Gemara actually had that the
measurements changed. It changed from how they were measured in the when
in the in the מדבר Midbar based on the תורה's Torah measurement,
then it's called סאה מדברית. Se'ah Midbarit. Then it's סאה ירושלמית Se'ah
Yerushalmit when it came in the sort of times of the kings
and it came to ירושלים, Yerushalaim, then the measurement became a larger
amount. The same name referred to a larger amount. And then סאה
ציפורית Se'ah Tziporit when they came to like the Rabbinic period, it
grew even more and the same measurement meant even yet more than
that. Okay? So they keep on increasing what the measurement means. So
the גמרא Gemara says which type of סאה Se'ah are you talking
about?
אי דמדברית Ei d'Midbarit קמד Kuf Mem Dalet הויה. Havya.
So if it's this math that we did, right? Six קב Kav
and 6 times 24, it's 144, that's not 217. ואי דירושלמית, V'ei
d'Yerushalmit, if it's Jerusalem סאה, Se'ah, קעג Kuf Ayin Gimmel הויה. Havya.
It's 173 because here's the math, okay? The basic assumption is, I'll
erase that, assume you've all got that, it'll be on the test,
make sure it's in your notes. Okay, so that was a joke.
Okay, so we have one סאה Se'ah equals six קב Kav and
at the rate of one קב Kav equals 24 ביצים, Beitzim,
we have 144. Now, that is a מדברית Midbarit סאה. Se'ah. The
ירושלמית Yerushalmit is 20 percent larger. Okay? So a
ירושלמית Yerushalmit סאה Se'ah equals 1.2 of a מדברית Midbarit סאה. Se'ah.
It's 20 percent larger. Okay? So it contains 20 percent more. So
what's this plus 20 percent?
So 0.2 times this is
28.8, right?
So you add it, 28.8, and you get
.8, 2, 172.8.
Okay? And that's what it says. So it's roughly rounds it out.
ואי דירושלמית V'ei d'Yerushalmit קעג, Kuf Ayin Gimmel, 173 הויה. Havya. ואי
דציפורית, V'ei d'Tziporit, ציפורית Tziporit is another 20 percent larger than that,
רז Resh Zayin הויה. Havya.
So here's ציפורית, Tziporit, right? Which is 1.2 of ירושלמית. Yerushalmit.
So what's 1.2 of, let's round this off to 173. What's 1.2?
So that becomes 6, 14, what am I
doing? 2, 3, 34.6. So you add that,
7, 0, 207.6. Got it? Yes? Okay, so that's רז Resh Zayin
rounding down הויה. Havya. Okay? So anyway, you're not getting to 217.
At most what you get to is 207. How does רבי Rebbi
get 217? So the גמרא Gemara says לעולם דציפורית, L'olam d'Tziporit, it
is ציפורית, Tziporit, but אייתי חלתא שדי עלייהו, Aiti chalta shadi aleihu,
but we're talking about the amount of this amount of wheat plus
the amount you'd have to take in order to be מפריש חלה.
Mafrish Challah.
If you were making חלה Challah out of this. Now when you're
מפריש חלה, Mafrish Challah, it's 1/24th. Okay? So what's 1/24th of this?
So 1/24th of what you have, what you get when you add
it to it?
Yeah, that is true. But we're going to ignore that right now.
Okay, I mean, it's not going to make a significant enough difference.
Okay? So 24th is basically 8, look, if you do the math,
right? 16, 32, 2, 3, 16,
192. So it's a little more. It's 8 and change. Okay? We
need to get 10 more. 8 and change is not going to
do it for us. Okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
חלתא כמה הויה? Chalta kama havya? Where am I? הויין תמני. Havyan
tamni. So the חלה Challah is only 8 more. אכתי בציר ליה,
Achti batzir lei, it's still not to 217. Of course, if you
didn't keep on rounding, it probably would be very close, but we
won't worry about that. אלא אייתי ועודות דרבי. Ela aiti v'odot d'Rebbi.
Ah, remember we had said that all of these numbers were imprecise.
So רבי Rebbi said that when you do all of the subdivisions,
right? It's really it's plus a little bit, right? It's a ועוד,
V'od, which we said is 1/20th. So רבי Rebbi said when we
have your normal קב, Kav, which is when we have your normal
סאה, Se'ah, which is 144 ביצים, Beitzim, okay? So but every ביצה
Beitzah really is an extra
1/20th of, you know, of, it's not really those ביצים, Beitzim, it's
those ביצים Beitzim plus a 20th. So how's the math going to
work? ועודות דרבי, V'odot d'Rebbi, hold on,
שדי עלייהו, Shadi aleihu, and put it on it. So if you
add a 20th, it's almost transparent, right? What's a 20th of 207
roughly? 10. Right? 20 divided by 207 is plus 10. And therefore
you get 217. Okay, because every ביצה... Beitzah... In this measurement, it's
not really 144 ביצין, beitzin, it's really 144 ביצין beitzin and plus
one 20th of a ביצה. beitza. Okay, so if you really want
to get the numbers, you have to multiply it by a 20th.
Alright, so there you go. So the גמרא Gemara says, where are
we? אי הכי הוי ליה טפי, ee hachi havei lei tefei, but
it's not exactly 217, it's 217 and change, which they've been sort
of ignoring until now. So כיון דלא הוי כביצה, keivan delo havei
kebeitza, since it's not a full number, לא חשיב ליה, lo chashiv
lei, fine, we're just rounding to the nearest number, okay? So that's
how you get 217. So all this is A, an introduction to
the idea that the sizes grew, and B, that the ביצה beitza
measurement is imprecise. When we measure a סאה se'ah in terms of
ביצים, beitzin, it's really in terms of a ביצה beitza plus a
20th according to רבי. Rebbi.
Why do we need to know this just because?
Yeah, because it has implications for all these, for various הלכות. halachos.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
תנו רבנן, Tanu rabbanan, סאה ירושלמית יתירה על מדברית שתות. Se'ah Yerushalmis
yesera al Midbaris shtos. A Jerusalem קב kav is more than the
wilderness קב kav by a sixth. Now I said it's 1.2 of
the סאה se'ah because 1.2, the way the גמרא Gemara does the
math, you would have said it's 20% larger, but a sixth of
the end result, a sixth of 1.2 is 0.2, so it's a
sixth of it after you do the math. Okay, but we'll say
it's 20% larger, but they say it's a sixth. Okay, שתות. shtos.
ושל ציפורי יתירה על ירושלמית שתות. Veshel Tzipori yesera al Yerushalmis shtos.
And the ציפורי Tziporis is more than the ירושלמית Yerushalmis another sixth,
which really means 20% from your original number. נמצא של ציפורי יתירה
על מדברית שליש. Nimtza shel Tzipori yesera al Midbaris shelish. Now this
is going to be a problematic math. If A is a sixth
bigger than B, and B is a sixth bigger than A, and
C is a sixth bigger than B, so a sixth and a
sixth makes two sixths makes a third, C is a third bigger
than A. Of course that's not true. Okay, because it's, you know,
it's times the previous one. And besides which, it's not really a
sixth, it's really a fifth. So if you ask yourself, what is
the relationship of a ירושלמית Yerushalmis to a, to a ציפורי Tzipori
to a מדברית, Midbaris, it's 1.2 times 1.2, which is what, 144?
Yeah, so it's right, so it's 1.44. 1.44 right, so it's 1.44
bigger, which is not a third. And even if you do it
in the opposite way of the גמרא, Gemara, you're not going to
get a third, I don't think. Because what would be a third
of this? A third of 1.44 is 4, what's a third of
1.44? 0.48
right,
so it's not 1. because that, you needed to, you would need
it to be 44. Anyway, so that's the real answer, but the
גמרא Gemara says it's a third bigger, meaning 1.33, which is also
not true, and the גמרא Gemara knows it's not true. So let's
take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. שליש דמאן?
Shelish de'man? A third of which measure? the גמרא Gemara says. Now
it's going to get confusing. אילימא שליש דמדברית, Eilima shelish de'Midbaris, if
it's a third bigger than the original
מדברית Midbarit one, מכדי שליש דמדברית כמה הויין? michdi shelish de'Midbaris kama
havyan? A מדברית, Midbaris, remember, was how many eggs?
144. Right, 100 and no, 144, okay. So what's a third of
144? שליש דמדברית כמה הויין? Shelish de'Midbaris kama havyan? ארבעין ותמניא, arba'in
u'tmanya, 48. Alright, so 48 is a third of that. So but
the difference now, right, we have 207 is here and 144 is
here. So what's the actual difference of those two? 207, the actual
difference is
3, is 63, right? Yes, the actual difference is 63. Okay, now
if you took a third of this, that's a 48 difference, it's
not a 63 difference.
Okay, so that third doesn't work. Do people see what I'm doing?
Okay, the thing, a third, this, this ירושלמית Yerushalamis is a third
bigger than the מדברית. Midbaris. 207 is a third more than that.
That's 44% bigger, but so it's really 63 bigger, 63 eggs bigger.
So and a third of 144 will not give you 63 eggs.
So the
גמרא Gemara says, where were, אילימא שליש דמדברית מכדי שליש דמדברית כמה
הויין ארבעין ותמניא ואילו עודפא שיתין ותלת, eilima shelish de'Midbaris michdi shelish
de'Midbaris kama havyan arba'in u'tmanya v'ilu udfa shitin v'slas, but the actual
difference is
63. אלא שליש דירושלמית. Ella shelish d'Yerushalmis. It's a third of the
ירושלמית. Yerushalmis. So what's a third of
207? 6, 18, 27, 69, right? Which is too big, it's not
63. שליש דידה כמה הויין? Shelish d'didah kama havyan? Wait a minute,
did I skip a line? Oh no, I went, I went to
ציפורי. Tzipori. First we're going to try a third of the, a
third of the ירושלמית. Yerushalmis. So a third of 173 is
5, 23, 57 and change. Okay, so
שליש דידה כמה הויין חמשים ותמניא, shelish d'didah kama havyan chamishin v'tmanya,
58 rounding, נכי תילתא, nechi tilta, minus a third, so it's 57
and change. ואילו עודפא שיתין ותלת, v'ilu udfa shitin v'slas, but we
see that the difference is
63. אלא דציפורי. Ella d'Tzipori. Fine, a third of the this, but
a third of this is what did we just say it was?
It was about seventy, okay sixty-nine or something. שלישתא דכמה הוין shlishta
d'kama havin שבעין נכי חדא shiv'in n'chi chada sixty-nine. ואילו אוצפא v'ilu
otzpa but the actual difference is ס"ג samech gimmel sixty-three. So this
idea of a six and a six and you get a third
doesn't work no matter what it's a
third of. So אלא אמר רב ירמיה הכי קאמר ela amar reb
yirmiah hachi ka'amar נמצא סאתה של ציפורי יתירה על מדברי קרוב לשליש
nimtza sa'ata shel tzipori yetera al midbari karov l'shlish, שלה. shela The
okay, so the difference here of the of the Tziporis to the
one more time, סאתה של ציפורי יתירה על המדברי sa'ata shel tzipori
yetera al hamidbari is about a third of it, hold on one
minute.
Right. So a third of this is sixty-nine. Okay, a third of
the two hundred and seven, a third of the Yerushalmi is sixty-nine.
So that's pretty close to sixty-three. So the Yerushalmi is bigger than
the than the midbarit, meaning we said sixty-nine isn't sixty-three, he basically
sticks in the word approximately, close to.
Okay? So נמצא סאתה של ציפורי nimtza sa'ata shel tzipori יתירה על
מדברי yetera al midbari קרוב לשליש, it's about a third more שלה
of its own of its own size. ושליש שלה ushlish shela and
a third of it is קרוב למחצה דמדברי. karov l'machtza d'midbari. By
the way, if you were interested, this sixty-nine is also about half
of the is about half of the original size, right? Because half
of seventy-four is seventy-two? So this one-third of this measure is about
is this is about the difference between the two and somehow half
of the original of the original one. So the Gemara says what
are you doing sticking all those words into it? So the Gemara
says מתקיף לה רבינא matkif lah ravina מידי קרוב קרוב קתני? midi
karov karov katani? What, did it say about about? It says it's
the same. אלא אמר רבינא הכי קאמר ela amar ravina hachi ka'amar
נמצא שליש של ציפורי nimtza shlish shel tzipori the third of the
Tzipori בעודפתה של רבי b'odfatah shel rebbi if you're using the additional,
you know, little bit of the beitza, so you do a third
not of two hundred and seven but a third of two hundred
and seventeen. What do you get if you do a third of
two hundred and seventeen? Seventy-two and a little bit of a change,
right? Okay, so what is that? שליש של ציפורי בעודפתה של רבי
shlish shel tzipori b'odfatah shel rebbi יתירה על מחצה של מדברי שליש
ביצה yetera al machtza shel midbari shlish beitza is almost exactly half
of the midbarit. Now it's also crazy because the original Beraita said
the difference between this and this is a third. We have now
changed it to say not that the difference is a third, but
that a third of this, corrected for Rebbi, a third of this
is about half of that. All right, anyway, it was a hard
Beraita, that's the best the Gemara could do. Moving on.
What do the Yeshiva boys do who don't have any math in
their I
don't know what to tell you. How often do they learn this
daf in Yeshiva? תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. Okay, that was that was
challenging. Now we get a little bit one point left, but actually
this is
הלכה למעשה. halacha l'ma'aseh. ראשית עריסותיכם. reshit arisoteichem. You have to take
challah, the first of the offerings, right, the first of your kneading
of your kneading troughs. Whatever, your kneading things.
כדי עיסותיכם k'dei isoteichem עיסותיכם, isoteichem, the normal size of the bread
that you would make in the wilderness.
וכמה עיסותיכם? v'kama isoteichem? כדי עיסת מדבר, k'dei isat midbar, bread you
would make in the wilderness. That's that's the size that you're
chayav
in challah. וכמה עיסת מדבר? v'kama isat midbar? How much would it
be? דכתיב d'chtiv והעומר עשירית האיפה הוא. v'ha'omer asirit ha'eiphah hu. An
omer is a tenth of an ephah. Now an ephah is three
se'ah.
Okay? So an omer is therefore, and they would make the bread
from the omer, so the the omer is the omer of man,
the omer is point three of a se'ah. You with me here?
Okay. And this is מדברית, midbarit, this is the one that they
would use, the se'ah they would use in the wilderness. So it's
point three of a se'ah and a se'ah is one hundred and
forty-four, so you do the math, do the math.
One hundred and forty-four times three, twelve, twelve, thirteen, three, four, three,
forty-three point two beitzas.
And for anybody who's ever done challah, you know that that is
the size, how often do you do forty-three point two beitzas of
challah at home, but that is the size where you're chayav in
challah דאורייתא, d'orayta, forty-three point two beitzas. Okay. מכאן
אמרו mikan amru ז' רבעים קמח ועוד חייבת בחלה. zayin reva'im kemach
v'od chayavet b'challah. Seven reva'im, which is... sorry, ז' רבעים, zayin reva'im,
I'm sorry, seven reva'im, and a reva is six beitzas, okay,
it's a quarter of a kav and a kav is twenty-four beitzas,
so a reva is six beitzas, so seven reva'im plus a little
is chayav in challah. So seven times six is forty-two, the little
is one point one point two, you'll take my word for it,
and it's forty-three point two.
שהן ו' של ירושלמיות שהן ה' של ציפוריות. shehen vav shel yerushalmiyot
shehen hey shel tziporiyot. And interestingly though, now when you do the
conversion it actually works out perfect because if seven plus change... I
won't... if how much does seven plus change from this become in
the larger measurement? So for the larger measurement it's one point two
is... which is what, which is six-fifths, then to get to the
smaller measurement you multiply by five-sixths, right? People here with me? So
anyway, so if you do the seven and change, but if you
just did seven it would be thirty-five sixths, but the change gets
you to thirty-six sixths, so this becomes six down here and then
multiplying by five-sixths becomes five down here. Okay, so in the larger
measures, seven and change is six in this measure and five in
that measure. Okay, but that's not measured in ביצים, beitzas, that's measured
in רבע. reva. You have to multiply by six to get ביצים.
beitzas. One minute.
מכאן אמרו, mikan amru, from here they said, האוכל כמידה זו, ha-ochel
k'middah zo, if you eat this amount, oh my God, imagine eating
this amount. I have no idea what this last line means, right,
if you eat forty-three ביצים beitzas worth of bread, הרי זה ברי,
harei zeh bari, healthy, ומבורך, umvorach, and blessed. יתר כאן רעבתן, yaser
kahn ra'avtan, if you eat more than that, then you're like ravenous,
you're too big of a פרעסער. fresser. פחות מכאן, pachos mikan, מקולקל
במעיו, mekukul be'mayav, but if you eat less than that, your stomach
will be a mess. Now again, maybe this does not mean this
amount, maybe it means when you do all the subdivisions and you
eat the size of a סעודה seuda that we were talking about.
I really don't know, I don't know if your English gives interpretation
explanations of this, but I don't know who the heck is eating
forty-three point two ביצים. beitzas. I would like to say also that
what's perfect about this is also the mentality most people have about
religion, right? Where I am is exactly the right amount, anybody a
little bit to my right is a crazy פרום יאק frum-yak and
מחמיר, machmir, and anybody to my left is an אפיקורוס, apikores, and
I'm exactly the right amount. Yes, they're talking about the baker. All
these measures, everybody refers to just only the baker who bakes
this or the average person?
Yeah,
that's the thing. It assumes some perfect average, you know, and that
was sort of like what Rivka was asking. It's being very precise
about an inherently imprecise measure.
Is it measured in the bakers who bake only?
I think they're talking to everyone. All right, let's take a look
now. I'm moving on. I am moving on. Next משנה. mishna. אנשי
חצר ואנשי מרפסת. anshei chatzer v'anshei mirpeset. So אנשי חצר. anshei chatzer.
Right.
So now the purpose of this exercise, the purpose of this exercise
was so that you would be relieved to get back to talking
about חצר. chatzer. So,
we are talking now here, you've got your you've got like you've
sort of like got the motel situation I mentioned to you, you've
got here about, you know, a מרפסת. mirpeset. You've got people down
here that use the courtyard directly, okay, and this is the balcony.
Now, what we're going to find out though is, I need a
new pen. What? I know, I need a new pen. Anyway, we're
going to find out is is that, oh, God bless you. I
notice you didn't bring it out when we had the
half.
I was thinking about it, but I didn't want to.
Oh, that's so much better.
Okay, anyway, okay, fine. Anyway, you have the people down here, now
the people that use the balcony, it's not exactly like the hotel
situation because it doesn't open straight on. Apparently they get down to
the balcony, this becomes clear in the גמרא gemara by a ladder,
and then from here they get down into the courtyard. Okay, so
that's the case. Now they each group made their own עירוב, eruv,
but they didn't make an עירוב eruv together. So let's take a
look. What happens?
So, אנשי חצר ואנשי מרפסת ששכחו ולא עירבו. anshei chatzer v'anshei mirpeset
sheshachchu velo eirvu. They forgot and they did not make an עירוב
eruv together. כל שגבוה עשרה טפחים למרפסת, kol shegavoha asarah tefachim l'mirpeset,
פחות מכאן לחצר. pachos mikan l'chatzer.
So anything that is, if you have like a mound on the
ground here, you know, and you have some type of a, you
know, I don't know what you've got, but anyway, who again, it's
the question of who gets to use, remember like the wall between
the two courtyards, who gets to use this mound? Is it, you
know, you can use the חצר, chatzer, you can use the מרפסת.
mirpeset. How about something that is not flat on the ground and
is not totally equal, you know, totally level with the מרפסת? mirpeset?
You've got a ground over there. So I can maybe stand here
and I don't know, if it's not too far away and it's
pretty high, put something on it, and you can stand here and
put something on it. Whose yard is this? Is this my yard
or is it your yard? And that determines who gets to use
it. Okay, so it says כל שגבוה עשרה טפחים, kol shegavoha asarah
tefachim, if it's ten טפחים tefachim or higher, למרפסת, l'mirpeset, it's no
longer connected to the חצר, chatzer, although as we pointed out, ten
טפחים tefachim is about three feet, which is like ideally usable, you
know, to people in the courtyard. It seems to be a lot
harder to bend down and use something than it would to put
something on something three feet high. But halachically, once it's more than
ten טפחים tefachim off the ground, it's no longer part of the
ground and it's connected to the מרפסת. mirpeset. Does the מרפסת mirpeset
be three feet up in the air? Yeah, well the גמרא gemara
will talk about that. Okay, and it's connected to the מרפסת. mirpeset.
פחות מכאן לחצר, pachos mikan l'chatzer,
less than that, it's connected to the חצר. chatzer. חוליית הבור והסלע,
chuyas habor vehasela,
if you have for example a structure around a well, they would
sort of mound dirt around a well, or you have a rock,
so same הלכה. halacha. This is just applying what we just said.
גבוהים עשרה טפחים למרפסת, gvohim asarah tefachim l'mirpeset, if it's ten טפחים
tefachim high or higher, it's part of the it's part of the...
the balcony area. פחות מכאן לחצר, pachot mikan l'chatzer, less than that
it's to the חצר. chatzer. במה דברים אמורים bameh devarim amurim בסמוכה.
bismucha. Now that's only if this mound is close, I mean if
this mound is ten feet away from the balcony, how can you
say it relates to the balcony? So only if the mound is
close to the balcony. How close? וכמה היא סמוכה vekama hi smucha
ובאיזה היא סמוכה? uv'eizeh hi smucha? כל שאינה רחוקה ארבעה טפחים. kol
she'eina rechoka arba'a tfachim. Very close. It has to be within about
a foot. Okay? So if you've got a mound that is very
close to the balcony, it's within a foot of the balcony and
it's עשרה טפחים asara tfachim high or more, then it's considered part
of the balcony's ground. Anything else, lower or further away, is considered
part of the חצר's chatzer's ground. Let's see the גמרא. Gemara.
So פשיטא, pishita, the גמרא Gemara says it's obvious, although almost nothing
is obvious in this מסכת. masechet. פשיטא pishita לזה בפתח ולזה בפתח,
laze b'petach ulaze b'petach, היינו חלון שבין שתי חצרות. hainu chalon shebein
shtei chatzerot.
Let's say you've got what we're going to do now is we're
going to remember we had the case about the, right, two yards
and the wall between them, which is essentially the same question. Who
has rights to the whose wall was it? So the גמרא's Gemara's
going to sort of try to sort of abstract that question. So
first it says לזה בפתח ולזה בפתח, laze b'petach ulaze b'petach, this
one has פתח petach as a metaphor meaning Rashi sees it as
a metaphor not literal, easy access. So you've got a case of
this courtyard and you have this courtyard and you have some space,
it's not exactly clear whether we're talking about another courtyard or what
we're talking about, you have some space that is easy access to
both. Okay, who has rights to it? So the גמרא Gemara says
היינו חלון hainu chalon right היינו חלון שבין שתי חצרות. hainu chalon
shebein shtei chatzerot.
It would be analogous to the idea that you had here let's
say a wall and you had a חלון chalon in the wall,
which is very easy to use by both and okay, so here
too very easy to use by both. What's the הלכה? halacha? So
without saying it, the הלכה halacha is neither of them can use
it. Right? Remember where they were both competing for the space now,
you can use put stuff maybe in the חלון, chalon, well we'll
talk about that later. Using it means taking from the חלון chalon
into your courtyard. So if they both had equal easy access to
the window or to a separate yard then they're competing, they didn't
make an עירוב eiruv themselves and it's not שייך shayach to either
of their domain and therefore you cannot take stuff from that domain
into your domain. Okay, so that's, you might be able to move
within the domain itself but you can't take from one to the
other because they're equal competitors for that domain.
Assume that the domain straddles both equally. Like let's say 50% of
the...
yeah, yeah, that's the point, it's equal access. We'll talk about unequal
access in a minute. לזה בזריקה ולזה בזריקה, laze bizrika ulaze bizrika,
let's say both courtyards can get onto some other space by throwing
something on it. It's not easy access like just walk or put
it in a window, but it's higher up but you can have
equal hard access to it. So היינו כותל שבין שתי חצרות. hainu
kotel shebein shtei chatzerot. So that was the משנה Mishna case a
while ago. The wall. When you have a wall that's you know
and it again nothing you know it's equally it's hard access, it
might be ten feet high, it might be only עשרה טפחים, asara
tfachim, but the fact that it's equally hard this is equally easy
and this is equally hard and either way the point is they're
equal on both sides so no it's not connected to either one
in particular and neither one can use it to go from there
to its courtyard.
Okay. Now לזה בשלשול ולזה בשלשול, laze b'shilshul ulaze b'shilshul, how about
if it's the opposite, I mean same point, it's hard access but
rather than hard access high, it's hard access low. This one can
use it by stooping down like it's a ditch and the other
one can use it by stooping down. היינו חריץ שבין שתי חצרות.
hainu charitz shebein shtei chatzerot. Fine, that would be a ditch between
two courtyards. And again the assumption about all of these is is
that it's אסור assur to both. Okay, it's not connected to it.
So the basic point is if it's equal, nobody wins. Now לזה
בפתח ולזה בזריקה, laze b'petach ulaze bizrika, let's say one courtyard has
easy access and the other one only can get to it by
throwing, right? So you have some scenario like you know like you
know like different heights of
the you know these are different heights so you have a wall,
we had that before, which is much higher on this side than
it is on that side. Okay, so one has easy access and
the other and you on one side it's less than עשרה טפחים
asara tfachim and the other it's higher than עשרה טפחים. asara tfachim.
And the other has hard access, one can get to it only
by throwing, the other can get to it directly. So in that
case היינו
דרבה בר רב הונא אמר רב נחמן. hainu derabba bar rav huna
amar rav nachman. That was what we said earlier of רבה בר
רב הונא Rabba bar Rav Huna in the name of רב נחמן
Rav Nachman about exactly this case about a wall that's עשרה טפחים
asara tfachim high on one side and less on another side and
it goes to the one that has the easy access. So so
far this has been a long way of saying a simple point,
which is if it's equally easy or equally hard then they're competing
and neither of them gets it. If it's easy for one and
hard for the other then the one it's easy for gets it.
Especially if the line of difference is higher than עשרה טפחים asara
tfachim for one and lower than עשרה טפחים asara tfachim for the
other. Now לזה בשלשול laze b'shilshul לזה בפתח ולזה בשלשול, lizeh b'petach
velizeh b'shilshul,
this is the same, just flipped. One has easy access and the
other has hard access, has to stoop down and get
it, so it's
היינו דרב שיזבי אמר רב נחמן. hainu d'Rav Shizbi amar Rav Nachman.
That was Rav Shizbi amar Rav Nachman said before, which was a
ditch between two courtyards that on one courtyard it's ten deep and
on the other it's less than ten deep. So for one it's
less than ten, and the other it's ten or more, it goes
to the one that it's less than ten. Now here is the
interesting question because all of that was obvious. If it's equal, no
go. If it's unequal, it goes to the one to whom it's
more accessible. But what about if it's equal but in different ways?
לזה בשלשול ולזה בזריקה מאי? lizeh b'shilshul velizeh b'zirika mai? One side
can access it by throwing and one side can access it by
stooping down. Is it more connected to one than the other? Okay,
now you ask me, maybe it's because I'm old and I worry
about my back, stooping down is much harder access than getting up.
Okay, so that is going to be, just to know where the
גמרא Gemara is getting to, that's going to be this case. This
case of the mound, right, even if it's higher than ten טפחים,
tefachim, I can only get it by throwing, it's higher than ten
means it's to some degree out of my domain. But the גמרא
Gemara says, but it's also lower than ten from if you start
from up here, from where the house is really are, right, then
it's more than ten this way. So it's greater than ten going
down and it's greater than ten going up. Okay, so who is
it more connected to? The one who has to go up or
the one who has to go down? In both of them, there
are hard access in both directions. So what's the הלכה? halacha? So
מאי? mai? אמר רב שניהם אסורין. amar Rav shneihem asurin. So they're
still basically equal. Hard access both sides, they're both
אסור. assur. ושמואל אומר נותנים אותו לזה שבשלשול. uShmuel omer nosnim oso
lizeh sheb'shilshul. You give it to the guy that has to stoop
down. Why? שלזה תשמישו בנחת ולזה תשמישו בקשה. shelizeh tashmisho b'nachas velizeh
tashmisho b'kasha. This one can use it easily and the other difficult.
Again, if you think about bending, I don't get it, but maybe
the idea is if you have to throw something on a wall,
you have no access to it, whereas if it's like reaching down,
you get a hanger or you get a broom or you get
something, it's maybe somewhat easier access. So he says it goes to
the guy who
gets it by stooping down.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, וכל דבר שתשמישו לזה בנחת
ולזה בקשה, vechol davar shetashmisho lizeh b'nachas velizeh b'kasha, anytime it's easy
for one and hard for the other, נותנים אותו לזה שתשמישו בנחת.
nosnim oso lizeh shetashmisho b'nachas. You give it to the one to
whom it's easier. תנן. tnan. Now how does this work in our
משנה? mishna? אנשי חצר ואנשי מרפסת ששכחו ולא עירבו, anshei chatzer ve'anshei
mirpeset sheshachachu velo eirvu, they forgot and they didn't make an עירוב.
eiruv. כל שגבוה עשרה טפחים למרפסת. kol shegavoah asarah tefachim lemirpeset. If
it's ten טפחים tefachim it goes to the balcony. פחות מכאן
לחצר. pachas mikan lachatzer. So קסלקא דעתך, kesalka daitach, מאי מרפסת? mai
mirpeset? we assumed what did מרפסת mirpeset mean? בני עליה. bnei aliyah.
It didn't mean for the people down here on the מרפסת, mirpeset,
it meant for the people up here on the actual attic. And
there it really is higher than ten on one and lower than
ten for the other, lower than ten for one. ומאי קרי ליה
מרפסת? umai kari lei mirpeset? Why do they call it a
מרפסת? mirpeset? דכסלקי במרפסת, d'kesalki b'mirpeset, because they go down to the
courtyard through the balcony. אלמא, alma, okay, but if that's what we're
talking about, כל לזה בשלשול ולזה בזריקה נותנים אותו לזה שבשלשול. kol
lizeh b'shilshul velizeh b'zirika nosnim oso lizeh sheb'shilshul. So you see, the
courtyard has it higher than ten, the people in the second story
it's lower than ten and you give it to the people in
the second story. So you see that is consistent with שמואל. Shmuel.
It's against רב. Rav. רב Rav said it's אסור. assur. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, כדאמר רב הונא לאותם הדרים במרפסת. k'd'amar Rav
Huna le'osam hadarim b'mirpeset. הכא נמי לאותם הדרים במרפסת. hacha nami le'osam
hadarim b'mirpeset.
We're not talking about the people up here. Actually there were two
stories and we're talking about the people that
live directly by the balcony. So for these people, it
actually is less than ten. Okay, so for these people it's nine,
for these people it's twenty, and for these people it's twenty. So
the גמרא Gemara says when we say you give it, we don't
mean you give it to the people up here according to
רב Rav because it's equally difficult for the people up here and
the people down here, so according to רב Rav no one gets
it. But for the people here, it's within nine of them and
it's more than ten for these, that's when we say we give
it to them. Okay, so we will end here with the debate
of רב ושמואל, Rav uShmuel, which is שמואל Shmuel says you always
prefer the people who have to go down over the people have
to go up, and רב Rav says if they're equally out of
access for both, then nobody gets it, they're considered equal.